<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>joakimbech.com - A trash can full of ideas - Tools</title><link href="https://jyx.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jyx.github.io/feeds/tools.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jyx.github.io/</id><updated>2018-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>What about Total Commander?</title><link href="https://jyx.github.io/blog/2010/03/12/what-about-total-commander/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-03-12T06:26:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Joakim Bech</name></author><id>tag:jyx.github.io,2010-03-12:/blog/2010/03/12/what-about-total-commander/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Total Commander logo" src="https://jyx.github.io/images/logo_tc.jpg" align="right"&gt;
As my first post on my new site I'll start by talking about Total Commander. I
have been using this wonderful tools since I think I got my first PC. Back then
it was called Windows Commander. So what is it that makes this tool so
wonderful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, if you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Total Commander logo" src="https://jyx.github.io/images/logo_tc.jpg" align="right"&gt;
As my first post on my new site I'll start by talking about Total Commander. I
have been using this wonderful tools since I think I got my first PC. Back then
it was called Windows Commander. So what is it that makes this tool so
wonderful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, if you just install it and start it you maybe won't be that
impressed. It has a quite old and perhaps boring look. But, if I can choose
between good looking tool without any features (Windows Explorer) and a not so
good looking tool with almost any features you can think of that is needed or
could be nice to have when it comes to file handling on a computer. Then I
choose the latter one. Which, in this case is Total Commander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you normally do with your files on your computer? For a normal user
you open files and maybe move files. That might be it for a big part of the
population. But if you are a slightly more advanced user? Then you might need to
duplicate files, pack/unpack files. You maybe want to filter the files so you
only will see files matching a certain pattern. You maybe want to synchronize
your files on a backup drive? Want to syntax hi-light files with certain name?
Copy file names with or without full path to clipboard? All of this and much
more you can do with Total Commander and as a good bonus there are quite easy
keyboard shortcuts for doing that. So you don't have to move one of you hands
between the keyboard and the mouse all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The look&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total Commander is composed as one main window with a split pane. First time I
saw this was back in time when Amiga 500 was a popular computer. I'm thinking of
the file manager &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directory_Opus"&gt;Directory Opus&lt;/a&gt;.
Is this a good or a bad thing? Well, since it still exists and seems to be quite
popular among people that have some higher demand on file exploring tool than
the average user have, then I think we can say, yes it's a good thing. To be
honest it's actually very good. You have two panes open all the time within the
same program, so you can very easy move, copy files etc. Since quite some time
ago Total Commander also supports tabs. Hence you can have multiple tabs for
both panes. You jump between the panes by simply pressing TAB and you jump
between tabs in the panes by pressing &lt;code&gt;CTRL + TAB&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Renaming on steroids&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something called Multi-Rename Tool in Total Commander which is quite
handy. It can rename a lot of files for you in very few clicks. Imagine you have
a folder with following files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    a_foo.zip
    b_foo.zip
    c_foo.zip
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now you want to rename those to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    01_a.zip
    02_b.zip
    03_c.zip
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Total Commander you simply mark the files and press &lt;code&gt;CTRL + M&lt;/code&gt; and the
Multi-Rename Tool will launch. In this particular example you prepend the
&lt;code&gt;Rename mask: file name&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;01_&lt;/code&gt; and in the &lt;code&gt;Search &amp;amp; Replace&lt;/code&gt; you write
&lt;code&gt;\_foo&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;Search For&lt;/code&gt;, like shown in the screenshot below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Total Commander multi rename tool" src="https://jyx.github.io/images/tc_multi_rename_tool.png" align="center"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can just imagine how helpful this is when you are renaming a couple of
hundred jpg files snapped with your digital camera where you often have quite
cryptic naming as default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shortcuts and some more features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could explain a bunch of features like the Multi-Rename Tool in detail. But
some features are very simple to use, so I list a couple of my daily things I do
using Total Commander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say you have &lt;code&gt;c:\a&lt;/code&gt; in the left pane and &lt;code&gt;c:\b&lt;/code&gt; in the right pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark files? Use &lt;code&gt;space&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;SHIFT + PgUp/PgDown&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;CTRL + plus&lt;/code&gt; or simply
press plus and make a filter out the files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to move files from folder &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;? Mark the files you want to move and
press &lt;code&gt;F6&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rename a file? &lt;code&gt;SHIFT + F6&lt;/code&gt;. This is a bit odd, since most other program have
&lt;code&gt;F2&lt;/code&gt; as rename button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pack files? Mark the files, &lt;code&gt;ALT + F5&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;ENTER&lt;/code&gt;. Files are now packed and
put into the folder on the other pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unpack files? Mark the files, &lt;code&gt;ALT + F9&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;ENTER&lt;/code&gt;. Files are unpacked to
the other pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Browse packed files? Simply press &lt;code&gt;ENTER&lt;/code&gt; on a zip file for example and you will
see the content immediately without unpacking it. Very useful! Note that you can
copy single files when in this state. This is also very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find files? &lt;code&gt;Alt + F7&lt;/code&gt;, then just search. Note the &lt;code&gt;Search subdirectories&lt;/code&gt; which
is very useful of you have a big project with a lot of subfolder but you know
that the file you are searching is not that deep down into the folder structure.
Then you use this to select how many subdirectories you want to traverse. Very
useful, especially in combination with the &lt;code&gt;Find text&lt;/code&gt; in the same window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to folders that you have been in? Press &lt;code&gt;ALT + down&lt;/code&gt; and you get a neat list
for the last ~30 folders you have been in. Note that this is unique for the
pane. I.e. one for the left pane and one for the right pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run a command? Just type it and press &lt;code&gt;ENTER&lt;/code&gt;. For example I want command
prompt. I simply type &lt;code&gt;cmd&lt;/code&gt; then press enter. Voila I get a command prompt
which have the path same to my current folder in my pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark a folder as favorite? Press &lt;code&gt;CTRL + d&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. Type any name you like to
refer to this folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to a favorite folder? Press &lt;code&gt;CTRL + d&lt;/code&gt; and select your favorite folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do a mouse right click? Press &lt;code&gt;SHIFT + F10&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View content of a file? Press &lt;code&gt;F3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit a file? Press &lt;code&gt;F4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Should you buy Total Commander?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, at least download it asap and start using it. If you just want to try it,
you will only get one(!) nag screen when starting the program. Then you can
leave it running for hours, days, weeks, years with full functionality and no
more nag screens. But, when you notice that you cannot really live without this
tool, then I think you should register the program. Christian Ghisler (the
author) deserves money for this great tool and he has given free updates since I
registered it, which was quite long time ago. As the headline says, I think
Microsoft should buy this tool/company and replace Windows Explorer with Total
Commander. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to the official site: http://www.ghisler.com&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>